Guide to the Earl J. Hamilton Papers, 1350-1995 and undated (bulk 1650-1940) RL.00496
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Earl J. Hamilton papers
1350-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hamilton, Earl J.
RL.00496
43.5 Linear Feet
32,625 Items
Collection spans the years 1350 to 1995, and contains Earl J. Hamilton's research notes and other materials dating chiefly from the 1930s to the 1970s. Hamilton was a pioneer in the field of quantitative economic history during a career that spanned fifty years. Together with his wife, Gladys Dallas Hamilton, he conducted important research during the 1930s and 1940s on the history of the South American and Spanish economies; the history of American, Spanish, and French banking; the history of John Law and the "Mississippi Bubble" and its effect on European economies; and prices and wages in medieval Spain.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Earl J. Hamilton Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1990-1992.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1899 Born in Houlka, Miss.
1920 Graduated with honors from the University of Mississippi
1923 Married Gladys Olive Dallas
1924 Received M.A. from University of Texas
1924-1926 Hamilton and his wife studied at Harvard, taking classes in history with Allyn Young; Earl Hamilton received A.M. in 1926
1927-1944 Professor of economics at Duke University
1928 Published article American Treasure and Andalusian Prices, 1503-1660: A Study in the Spanish Price Revolution, initiating the modern debate on profits and price inflation in Europe
1929, Nov. Published American Treasure and the Rise of Capitalism, 1500-1700 in Economica
1929 Received Ph.D. from Harvard
1934 Published American Treasure and the Price Revolution in Spain, 1501-1650 (Harvard University Press)
1936 Published Money, Prices, and Wages in Valencia, Aragon, and Navarre, 1351-1500 (Harvard University Press)
1936-1937 Published Prices and Wages at Paris Under John Law's System
1944-1947 Professor of economics at Northwestern University
1947 Published War and Prices in Spain, 1651-1800 (Harvard University Press)
1947-1967 Professor of economics at the University of Chicago
1948-1954 Served as editor of the University of Chicago's Journal of Political Economy
1951-1952 President of the Economic History Association
1966-1969 Distinguished Professor of Economic History at the State University of New York, Binghamton
1969 Published The Political Economy of France at the Time of John Law in History of Political Economy journal
1977, Mar. Published The Role of War in Modern Inflation in the Journal of Economic History
1989 Died in Oak Ridge, Tenn.
Collection Overview
The Earl J. Hamilton Papers span the years from 1350 to 1995, with Hamilton's research notes and other materials dating chiefly from the 1930s to the 1970s. (Note: Early dates reflect original dates of primary sources rather than the dates on which the photocopies of these sources were created.) Hamilton was a pioneer in the field of quantitative economic history during a career that spanned fifty years. Together with his wife, Gladys Dallas Hamilton, he conducted important research during the 1930s and 1940s on the history of the South American and Spanish economies; the history of American, Spanish, and French banking; the history of John Law and the "Mississippi Bubble" and its effect on European economies; and prices and wages in medieval Spain.
The collection includes not only extensive background notes for Hamilton's major books and articles, but also over 200 original legajos and other documents pertaining to Spanish trade and economic development, dating primarily from the 17th and 18th centuries. Other primary source materials from the 14th to the 18th centuries are also abundant (chiefly in the form of photostats and transcripts), including hundreds of copies of documents held by the Archivo del Banco de España, the Archivo Histórico Nacional, and other archives in Europe.
Photocopies and microfilm copies of items which belong to other libraries and archives may require permission of the owner institution to further reproduce or publish. Users making further copies for their own research do so at their own discretion. Before publication of any such material, it is the user's responsibility to identify the original source and obtain permission.
The collection also contains drafts and reprints of research papers, and numerous folders of academic and personal correspondence. Some documents in the collection are in French or Spanish.
Note that the early dates given in collection and series titles reflect the dates of the original primary source material that Hamilton used for his research, not the date when the photostat, photocopy or transcription was created.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the Teaching Materials Series is restricted. In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Contact Research Services for more information.
Spain -- Economic conditions; Spain -- Commerce -- History; Monroe Doctrine -- Economic aspects; Prices -- Spain -- History; Europe -- Economic conditions; South America -- Economic conditions; France -- Economic conditions; Economics -- Study and teaching; Banks and banking -- Spain -- History; Banks and banking -- France -- History; Economists -- Correspondence; Historians -- Correspondence; Law, John, 1671-1729; Hamilton, Earl J.
- Biographical Data Series, 1930-1995 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Various materials recording details and events in Hamilton's life and career; includes a curriculum vita and a list of his publications. Arranged in original order.
  - Folder containing Earl J. Hamilton's curriculum vita; publications and articles; outline for book on Banco de España, 1971-1995 and undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified cassette recording of voice and music, undated (Box 1)
  - Clipping in Italian from La Epoca, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1967-1981 and undated (Box 1)
- Reprints Series, 1937-1949
  - Spanish Banking Schemes Before 1700, 1949 (Box 1)
  - The Foundation of the Bank of Spain (originally intended to form basis for the book), 1945 (Box 1)
  - Use and Misuse of Price History, 1944 (Box 1)
  - The Decline of Spain, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Prices and Wages in Southern France under John Law's System, 1937 (Box 1)
- Teaching Materials Series, 1927-1969 and undated
  Chiefly grade books, along with a few class exams.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Student Grade Books in this series are CLOSED to use.
  - Exams, 1939-1969 and undated (Box 1)
  - Grade books, [1940s]-[1960s] (Box 1)
    CLOSED. Contact Research Services staff.
  - Grade books, [1930s]-[1960s] (Box 1)
  - Grade books, 1927-1929, 1936, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Grade books, [1930s]-[1940s] (Box 1)
  - Academic finances, [1930s] (Box 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1919-1992 and undated (bulk 1930-1970)
  Academic correspondence, dealing with Hamilton's research in Spain, his letters as professor of economics, and his position as editor of the Journal of Political Economy and as president of the Economic History Association. Many of the date ranges overlap from folder to folder. Arranged in original groupings of folders as received, with original titles.
  - Correspondence:
    - [1940s]-[1970s] (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1970s], 2 folders (Box 2)
    - [1960s]-[1970s] (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1960s] (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - miscellaneous:
    - [1930s], [1960s]-[1970s] (Box 2)
    - [1930s] (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1960s] and undated (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1950s] and undated (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1960s] and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1950s] and undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence plus reprint/galley of "Economic Origins of Monroe Doctrine":
    - [1930s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - miscellaneous:
    - 1919, Aug. 26; [1920s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - academic and personal:
    - [1930s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 2)
    - [1930s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 2)
  - Various financial correspondence:
    - [1930s]-[1960s] (Box 2)
  - Academic and personal correspondence:
    - [1960s] and undated (Box 2)
    - [1950s]-[1970s], 1992, and undated (Box 2)
    - [1950s] (Box 2)
    - [1940s], [1960s]-[1970s], and undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence on papers, research: (Box 3)
    - [1950s]-[1960s] and undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence on research, papers, social science during World War II:
    - [1930s]-[1940s] (Box 3)
    - [1960s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous academic and personal correspondence:
    - 1959-1961 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - miscellaneous:
    - 1938-1981 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - personal:
    - [1920s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 3)
    - [1930s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - papers: (Box 4)
    - [1920s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1920s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1920s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1940s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1960s] (Box 4)
    - [1950s] and 1970 (Box 4)
    - [1920s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1940s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1940s]-[1950s] and undated (Box 4)
    - La estimacion del trabajo manual en la España del siglo XVIII; Callahan, [1960s] (Box 4)
    - [1960s]-[1970s] (Box 4)
    - [1950s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1930s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1950s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1930s]-[1970s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1930s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1930s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1950s] (Box 4)
    - [1930s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence - Duke; partial:
    - [1930s]-[1980s] and undated (Box 4)
    - [1920s]-[1990s] and undated (Box 4)
  - Correspondence:
    - [1920s]-[1930s], 1960s, 1980s and undated (Box 4)
    - [1920s]-[1960s], 1980s and undated (Box 4)
    - [1920s]-[1930s], [1960s], [1980s] and undated (Box 4)
  - Letters written in Spain:
    - 1932-1933 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence:
    - [1940s] and [1970s] (Box 4)
- Major Works Series, 1350-1961 and undated
  Background notes, transcriptions of original source material, photostats of Spanish archival material (especially that related to treasure imports), and worksheets for compiling prices and salaries in Spain from 1351 to 1800, all related to Hamilton's research for his major published works. Also, a large number of photostats of materials from the Archivo del Banco de España and the Archivo Histórico Nacional concerning the Bank of Spain, as well as notes and source transcriptions of Hamilton's work on this subject. This series contains many photocopies and microfilm copies of items which belong to other libraries and archives. Photocopies of materials gathered from other repositories by Earl J. Hamilton may require permission of the owner institution to further reproduce or publish. Users making further copies for their own research do so at their own discretion. Before publication of any such material, it is the user's responsibility to identify the original source and obtain permission.
  Divided into subseries for each major work; papers within are arranged in Hamilton's original order with original folder titles given.
  Note: Dates given below in the descriptions for primary source materials reflect the dates of the original items, not the more modern dates on which the photostats or transcriptions were created.
  - War and Prices in Spain, 1651-1800 Subseries, 1651-1944 and undated (Box 5)
    - Andalusia worksheets, 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Andalusia price worksheets, 1651-1787 (Box 5)
    - Andalusia, final commodity list, 1651-1800, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Old Castile prices, 3 folders
      - 1651-1700 (Box 5)
      - 1700-1750 (Box 5)
      - 1750-1800 (Box 5)
    - Andalusia, salaries and wages [original sheets] (Box 5)
    - Valencia, salaries [original sheets], 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Old Castile, dope sheets, 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Old Castile, typed prices, 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - New Castile, prices, 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Valencia, typed prices [copies], 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Old Castile, typed prices [carbons], 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Valencia, typed prices, 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Andalusia, typed prices, 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - New Castile, prices [copies], 1651-1800 (Box 5)
    - Old Castile, worksheets:, 3 folders
      - 1651-1712 (Box 5)
      - 1713-1760 (Box 5)
      - 1761-1800 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous notes and transcriptions to War and Prices and Money, prices, and wages, undated (Box 6)
    - New Castile, wages, 1651-1800 (Box 6)
    - War and Prices/Miscellaneous: Spanish Prices: A Reply to Dr. M.J. Elsos, 1937, June (Box 6)
    - Various worksheets for price and wage indices [checklists], 1651-1800 (Box 6)
    - War and Prices in Spain, typescript, 1651-1800, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - New Castile, original price sheets, 1651-1800 (Box 7)
    - Santo Tomas, prices/commodity worksheets:
      - 1651-1700 (Box 7)
      - 1701-1750 (Box 7)
      - 1750-1800 (Box 7)
    - Buyer's notebook, Hospital of the Innocents, various years; pricing/commodities worksheet, undated (Box 7)
    - Commodity/price worksheets, 1651-1691 (Box 7)
    - Valencia, commodities list, 1651-1800 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes and typescripts: War and Prices series (various years and undated) (Box 7)
    - Andalusia, related prices and figures, 1651-1700 (Box 7)
    - War and Inflation in Spain: 1780-1800, 1944, Nov. (Box 7)
    - Notes on "Treasure," undated (Box 7)
    - Tabulated quarterly wages and salaries; all four regions except Valencia, 1651-1800 (Box 7)
    - New Castile, worksheets, price relatives, indices:
      - 1651-1700 (Box 7)
      - 1701-1750 (Box 7)
      - 1751-1800 (Box 7)
    - New Castile and Andalusia, price relatives, worksheets, 1651-1800 (Box 7)
  - Money, Prices, and Wages in Valencia, Aragon, and Navarre, 1351-1500 Subseries, 1350-1451 (Box 8)
    - Navarre, prices/commodities, dope/worksheets:
      - 1350-1400 (Box 8)
      - 1401-1451 (Box 8)
    - Navarre, notes on prices, spreadsheets on wages, 1401-1450 (Box 8)
  - American Treasure and the Revolution in Spain Subseries, 1351-[192-?] and undated (Box 8)
    - Negatives in protective folder; Frontispiece to document used as Plate II, undated (Box 8)
    - Notes on weights, measures, grades of silver, commodities, various dates and undated (Box 8)
    - Treasure imports, photostats, various dates (Box 8)
    - Archival material pertaining to silver imports and to Valencia (photostats), 1501-1650 and undated (Box 8)
    - Navarre and related notecards, 1351-1500 (Box 8)
    - Various letters and notes related to money, prices, inflation; associated with major works, undated (Box 8)
    - American Treasure and the Rise of Capitalism, 1500-1700, [192-?] (Box 8)
    - "Treasure" imports, 1501-1650 (Box 8)
    - Valencia, prices/commodities, worksheets/dopes, 1501-1550 (Box 8)
  - Bank of Spain, 1651-1800 Subseries, 1360-1981 and undated (bulk 1700s-1800s) (Box 8)
    - Color prints commemorating Banco Nacional, [ca. 1780-1830] and undated (Box 8)
    - Banco de España, photostats of documents, undated (Box 8)
    - Junta General (photostats):
      - 1814, Apr. 21 (Box 8)
      - 1815, Apr. 20 (Box 8)
      - 1816 (Box 8)
      - 1817, Apr. 19 (Box 8)
      - 1818, Apr. 20 (Box 8)
      - 1820, Apr. 20 (Box 9)
      - 1821, Jan. 18 (Box 9)
      - 1821 (Box 9)
      - 1824, Apr. 26 (Box 9)
      - 1826 (Box 9)
      - 1827, Apr. 19 (Box 9)
    - Photostats of original documents, Bank of Spain, various dates, [18-?] and undated (Box 9)
    - Photostats of documents in Amsterdam Archive; Royal cedulas of Carlos IV, 1800-[1806?] (Box 9)
    - Notes/typescripts to article on Bank of Spain, [ca. 1780-1830] and undated (Box 9)
    - Course syllabus/memorandum, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Spreadsheets on French stocks, [178-?] (Box 9)
    - Photostats of Junta General; Banco de San Carlos, 1800, Apr. 19 (Box 9)
    - Payment of dividends, photostat, 1799 (Box 9)
    - Photostats of Junta General; Banco de San Carlos 1800, Apr. 20 (Box 9)
    - Banco de España, photostats, [179-?] and undated (Box 9)
    - Reglamentos de las Juntas Generales...del Banco General, photostat, 1794 (Box 9)
    - Documents from the Archive of Conde de Cabarrus about National Bank, photostats, [ca. 1780s-1830s] and undated (Box 9)
    - Assets (?), Banco de San Carlos, weekly/monthly accounts, photostats, 1783-1799 (Box 9)
    - Banco de San Carlos, graphs/notes, [1780s]-[1830s] (Box 9)
    - "Staatsschulden," Xerox of article, 1855 (Box 9)
    - Photostats of legajos: (Box 10)
      - Bonds/accounts of Banco de España, [ca. 1800-1840] (Box 10)
      - Banco de España Silver Exports, 1790-1802 (Box 10)
      - Report of the Junta General Banco Nacional, 1808, Apr. 20 (Box 10)
      - Junta General, Banco Nacional, fragment, 1807 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence of the Bank, [178-?] (Box 10)
      - Accounts, Correspondence, Shares of Bank, [17-]-[18-] (Box 10)
      - Concerning Accounts and Loans of Bank, 1809 (Box 10)
      - Report of Junta General on Banco Nacional, 1821 (Box 10)
      - Bank dividends, 1812-1819 (Box 10)
      - Pertaining to investigation of Bank's directors, [1780s] (Box 10)
      - Proceedings of Bank's directors, [1790s] (Box 10)
      - Pertaining to the Bank's accounts, [1780s] (Box 10)
      - Proceedings of the Junta General, 1821 (Box 10)
      - Accounts/balances, 1823 (Box 10)
      - Establishing the Banco Español de San Fernando, 1829 (Box 10)
      - Stockholders meeting, 1790 (Box 10)
      - Promotion of industry; uniforms, materials required by Army, [1780s] (Box 10)
      - Various confidential papers, accounts of Banco plus (in French) report of La Banque de Saint-Charles, [1780s] (Box 10)
      - Various confidential papers, accounts and reports of Banco, [1780s], 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Loans, [1790s] and undated, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Accounts and totals (adding machine tapes, notes) [appears to be part of research into Banco de San Carlos], 1760-1783 (Box 11)
    - Various calculations, handwritten and compiled by year, on operation of Bank, [1780s]-[1830s] and undated (Box 11)
    - Typescript of archival materials from Amsterdam (Dutch or German?) about financial dealings with Spain, [ca. 1780-1830] and undated (Box 11)
    - Amsterdam Archives material, 1671, 1660, 1777 (Box 11)
    - Article by Hausman and Neufeld, The Political Economy of Walpole's 1733 Tax Scheme, 1981 (Box 11)
    - Materials on Banco de San Carlos research, various dates and undated (Box 11)
    - Photocopies of Bank of Spain, various dates and undated (Box 11)
    - Loans to the king, 1360 and 1781 (photostats) (Box 11)
    - Manuscripts, transcripts and correspondence, including Hamilton's 1943 arrangements for research assistants in Spain (Box 11)
    - Reprint De Girobanken van Genua, 1924 (Box 11)
    - Typescript of legajos relating to Cabarrus and Bank, 1954 and undated (Box 11)
    - Financial information on Cabarrus, 1951 (Box 11)
    - Spanish Banking Schemes Before 1700, working copy and notes, undated (Box 11)
    - Spanish Banking Schemes Before 1700; and The Foundation of the Bank of Spain, 1945, June (Box 11)
    - The First Twenty Years of the Bank of Spain. I, II. 1782-1802, 1946, Feb.-Apr. (Box 11)
    - Plans for a National Bank in Spain, 1701-83, 1949, Aug. (Box 11)
    - Paper money/accounts (photostats), [1780s] (Box 11)
    - Plans for other national banking systems (as possible models for Bank of Spain), 1747 (Box 11)
    - Bank of Spain notes folded and included with notecards, various dates and undated (Box 11)
    - Typescripts of various original documents, various dates and undated (Box 11)
    - Report of the Junta de Hospitales (photostat), undated (Box 11)
    - On the operation of royal hospitals (photostat), 1786 (Box 11)
    - Papers on the Conde de Cabarrus (photostats), [1780s]-[1790s] and undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous notes, some pertaining to Bank of Spain research, various dates and undated (Box 11)
    - Typed transcripts of legajos, Archivo General de Simancas, Inventory of Archives on Banco de San Carlos, [ca. 1780-1830] and undated (Box 11)
    - Photostats of legajos: (Box 12)
      - Cabarrus Papers; Cabarrus made a Spanish subject and starting the bank, [ca. 1780-1830] and undated (Box 12)
      - Report of the junta to the king, dealing with bonds, 1794 (Box 12)
      - Memoria from Don Fr. Cabarrus to king about Bank, 1782 (Box 12)
      - "Minuta del decreto para la ereccion del Banco," [1780s] and undated (Box 12)
      - Agreements reached by first junta on Bank, [1780s] and undated (Box 12)
      - More on bank notes and bonds, 1796 and undated (Box 12)
      - On the opening of the Bank, [1780s] and undated (Box 12)
      - Recommendations/criticisms of fomenting industry, 1779 (Box 12)
      - The revised bank plan of Floridablanca, 1779 (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous, pertaining to banks, trade, vagabonds, 1778 and n.d (Box 12)
      - Correspondence of Cabarrus, 1783-84 and undated (Box 12)
      - Investment in the Bank, 1784 (Box 12)
      - Investments in Bank, Bank's Charter, 1782 (Box 12)
      - Subscriptions to the Bank, 1782 and undated (Box 12)
      - On 'reducciones' and abuses at Bank, also concerning cloth manufacturing, 1782 and undated (Box 12)
      - Assessment or probate and Accounts and Conde de Cady, 1799 (Box 12)
      - Declaration of Conde de Cabarrus to Inquiry, [1790s], 4 folders
        - pp. 1-50 (Box 12)
        - pp. 51-100 (Box 12)
        - pp. 101-150 (Box 12)
        - pp. 151-end, lengthy statement by Cabarrus about 'Auto' (Box 12)
- Research Papers Series, [ca. 1592]-1969 and undated
  Notes, transcriptions and photostats of primary sources, drafts of papers (both typed and written), lectures, and notecards, all relating to Hamilton's published and unpublished work on the economic origins of the Monroe Doctrine, South American wars of independence, Colombia, John Law, price and wages theory, and miscellaneous other topics. Arranged in original order with folder titles assigned by Hamilton.
  Note: Dates given below in descriptions of primary sources reflect the date of the original items, and not the modern date on which the photostats or transcripts were created.
  - Notes, business cards, letters, receipts, various dates and undated (Box 13)
  - Notecards, various dates and undated (Box 13)
  - Research notes and correspondence, various dates and undated, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Notes, book call numbers, clips, various dates and undated (Box 13)
  - Research on John Law:
    - Letters and notes, news clippings; various dates and undated (Box 13)
    - Papers, [1670s]-[1720s], 1967, May (Box 13)
    - Papers, [1670]-[1720s], 1967, May and 1969, Spring (Box 13)
    - Various notes and materials, [1670s]-[1720s] (Box 13)
    - The Political Economy of France at the Time of John Law, undated (Box 13)
    - Notes, various dates and undated (Box 13)
    - Various notes and materials (photostats, etc.), [ca. 1680-1720] (Box 13)
    - Various notes, [ca. 1680-1720], 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Various notes on Law and related subjects, [ca. 1680-1720] (Box 13)
    - Materials (Xeroxes, etc.), [ca. 1700-1720] (Box 13)
    - Un capitolo della vita di Giovanni Law, 1913-1914 (Box 13)
    - Materials: photographs and photostats, various dates and undated (Box 13)
    - Materials on the contemporaries of Law (i.e. Richard Cantillon), [ca. 1700-1720] (Box 13)
    - Various notes on Law and the financial system in early 1700s, 3 folders (Box 13)